<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cards on Relay Computer</title>
    <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cards on Relay Computer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2022 11:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Backplane</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/backplane/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2022 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/backplane/</guid>
      <description>Not a single card but actually one of four &amp;hellip; and technically not a card at all but they are card shaped. These are the &amp;lsquo;cards&amp;rsquo; that connect a group of five cards together in each card bay (W, X, Y and Z). Each carries a selection of lines and busses to the cards it holds and also hosts connections to the ribbon cables taking the busses and control lines of to other backplane cards and areas of the computer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Backplane Daughterboard</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/backplane-db/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2022 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/backplane-db/</guid>
      <description>Similar to the Backplanes themselves these are a specialised collection of cards. These &amp;lsquo;cards&amp;rsquo; are used in place of ribbon cables to pass the required signals and busses between a given backplane and other backplanes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decoder</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/decoder/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2020 03:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/decoder/</guid>
      <description>The decoder card takes its input from the instruction bus and decides which class of instruction the input represents. This is then used by the controller and sequencer cards in order to perform their tasks. The decoder card makes up part of the broader &amp;lsquo;control unit&amp;rsquo; within the computer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Controller</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/controller/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Dec 2019 03:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/controller/</guid>
      <description>The role of the controller card is to operate the various control lines of the computer at the right time according to the current instruction class. It makes up a key part of the broader &amp;lsquo;control unit&amp;rsquo; within the computer. It is primarily driven by the sequencer card to known &amp;lsquo;when&amp;rsquo; something should happen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sequencer</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/sequencer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2019 03:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/sequencer/</guid>
      <description>The sequencer card is effectively a Finite State Machine (FSM) and makes up the broader &amp;lsquo;control unit&amp;rsquo; within the computer. This card&amp;rsquo;s role is to produce a series of pulses at specified times that the controller card can then use to operate the various control lines of the computer at the right time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Register J</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/register-j/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2019 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/register-j/</guid>
      <description>The J Register is one of the specialised registers within the relay computer. It can hold two 8-bit values (J1 and J2) and can read (but not write) from the data bus. Additionally it can also write (but not read) a 16-bit value to the address bus combining the J1 and J2 8-bit registers together. Typically it is used to store the address for a jump on the GOTO instruction.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Register M</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/register-m/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2019 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/register-m/</guid>
      <description>The M Register is one of the general purpose registers within the relay computer. It can hold two 8-bit values (M1 and M2) and can read and write from/to the data bus. Additionally it can also write (but not read) a 16-bit value to the address bus combining the M1 and M2 8-bit registers together.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Register XY</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/register-xy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2019 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/register-xy/</guid>
      <description>The XY Register is one of the general purpose registers within the relay computer. It can hold two 8-bit values and can read and write from/to the data bus. Additionally it can also read and write a 16-bit value from/to the address bus combining the X and Y 8-bit registers together.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Auxiliary Control</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/aux-ctrl/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2018 22:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/aux-ctrl/</guid>
      <description>This card incorporates the primary input switches at the front of the computer and allows for a program to be loaded into memory (and confirmed) line-by-line. The 8-bit switches are set for each instruction and then deposited into memory. The card also contains a limited clock, sequencer and controller to operate the appropriate control lines and move the program counter on as necessary.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Incrementer</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/incrementer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2018 13:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/incrementer/</guid>
      <description>The incrementer card can take an input from the address bus and increment it by one placing the result in the increment register. This is primarily used to increment to program counter but also can increment the XY register too. The incrementer makes up the broader &amp;lsquo;control unit&amp;rsquo; within the computer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Memory</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/memory/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2017 21:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/memory/</guid>
      <description>The Memory card holds 32K of RAM and can hold both a program to execute as well as any associated data. It is one of a few &amp;lsquo;unauthenic&amp;rsquo; cards within the computer that is forced to use modern integrated circuits (ICs) to perform its role.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Program Counter</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/register-pc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Nov 2017 10:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/register-pc/</guid>
      <description>The Program Counter is one of the specialised registers within the relay computer. It holds a single 16-bit value representing the current location in memory of the program being executed. It can be read and written to from/to the address bus.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Display A</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/display-a/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2017 10:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/display-a/</guid>
      <description>Display A allows two way interaction with the user through illuminated switches. Firstly they show the state of the various control lines within the computer and secondly they allow the user to manually operate those lines when the computer is in the stopped state.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Display B</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/display-b/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2017 10:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/display-b/</guid>
      <description>Display B shows the status of the data, address and instruction busses along with ALU state, current instruction code class and finally the power being consumed in amps. Unlike Display A there is no interactive components/switches in this display.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Power Distribution</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/power-dist/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Oct 2017 11:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/power-dist/</guid>
      <description>The Power Distribution is a small card that takes the incoming power supply and splits it between the W, X, Y and Z backplanes and the front panel operations. Each power line has a 2A fuse to protect it in case of a short circuit or similar.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Instruction Register</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/register-i/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2015 10:19:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/register-i/</guid>
      <description>The Instruction Register is one of the specialised registers within the relay computer. It holds a single 8-bit value representing the current instruction to be performed. It is write-only (from the data bus) and has a permanent output on to the instruction bus.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Register A/D</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/register-ad/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2014 13:12:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/register-ad/</guid>
      <description>The A/D Register is one of the general purpose registers within the relay computer. It can hold two 8-bit values and can read and write from/to the data bus.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Register B/C</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/register-bc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2014 09:59:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/register-bc/</guid>
      <description>The B/C Register is one of the general purpose registers within the relay computer. It can hold two 8-bit values and can read and write from/to the data bus. Additionally this register also directly feeds in to the ALU providing its inputs. As such a value can&amp;rsquo;t be loaded to these registers whilst an ALU operation is in progress.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ALU Control Unit</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/control-unit/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2014 08:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/control-unit/</guid>
      <description>The Control Unit is one of the three cards making up the broader Artihmetic Logic Unit (ALU). This card handles function decoding, zero detection and holds the condition registers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ALU Arithmetic Unit</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/arithmetic-unit/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2014 17:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/arithmetic-unit/</guid>
      <description>The Arithmetic Unit is one of the three cards making up the broader Artihmetic Logic Unit (ALU). This card primarily handles 8-bit addition operations (adding together the inputs from register B and C) but can also perform an 8-bit increment (adding 1 to the input from register B). In either case the output from this card can then be loaded into register A or D.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ALU Logic Unit</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/logic-unit/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2013 08:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/logic-unit/</guid>
      <description>The Logic Unit is one of the three cards making up the broader Artihmetic Logic Unit (ALU). This card handles 8-bit binary logic operations (AND, OR, XOR of the inputs from register B and C) and 8-bit unary logic operations (NOT and SHL of the inputs from register B). In all cases the output from this card can then be loaded into register A or D.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Test Board</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/test-board/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2013 07:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/test-board/</guid>
      <description>Not a card as such (and not something that lives within the computer itself) but the test board is very useful in testing each of the cards as they&amp;rsquo;re completed. Effectively it&amp;rsquo;s just a series of buttons and so on the allow operation of the card, via its backplane connectors, in isolation of anything else in the computer.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
