<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>display-a on Relay Computer</title>
    <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/display-a/</link>
    <description>Recent content in display-a on Relay Computer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2017 10:47:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/display-a/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Miscellany Special: Backplane X, Cable Routing and Address Bus</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2017/11/miscellany-special-backplane-x-cable/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2017 10:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2017/11/miscellany-special-backplane-x-cable/</guid>
      <description>Continuing on with the theme from my last post &amp;hellip; here is another &amp;lsquo;miscellany special&amp;rsquo; covering all the little &amp;lsquo;side jobs&amp;rsquo; I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing on my relay computer alongside the primary work of constructing the Program Counter, Memory and Incrementer cards. There&amp;rsquo;s three things worth covering (plus an additional minor mention) &amp;hellip; let&amp;rsquo;s start with backplanes.
The computer is designed with four backplanes (W, X, Y and Z) each taking five cards.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More Laser Cut Parts</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2017/08/more-laser-cut-parts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Aug 2017 13:13:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2017/08/more-laser-cut-parts/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve nearly got the design for the memory cards done and ready to share but once that&amp;rsquo;s out the way it&amp;rsquo;ll be time to get on with some construction again. With that in mind I cracked out the credit cards and got buying more relays plus some other bits and bobs and whilst I was in a spending mood I decided it was high time to treat the computer to some more laser cut parts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>User Interface Construction: Instruction, Clock and Sequencer</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2016/03/user-interface-construction-instruction/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2016 22:38:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2016/03/user-interface-construction-instruction/</guid>
      <description>Well, the good news is I&amp;rsquo;ve just passed a major milestone in constructing this relay computer &amp;hellip; it can now perform a single instruction in full firing the various control lines as needed. The bad news &amp;hellip; I&amp;rsquo;m rather behind in blogging about it so this will be the first of a couple of &amp;lsquo;catch up&amp;rsquo; posts which will culminate in a video showing off the computer as it currently stands.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>User Interface Design: Instruction, Clock and Sequencer</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2015/04/user-interface-design-instruction-clock/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2015 23:19:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2015/04/user-interface-design-instruction-clock/</guid>
      <description>Over my last seven posts I&amp;rsquo;ve been slowly putting together the card designs so that the computer will be able to operate the MOV-8, ALU and SETAB instructions. The final step in this series is to update the designs for the two display cards along with the main switches to work with the new cards added recently.
Diving straight in here is the latest version of the Display A design:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>User Interface: Display A Initial Design and Construction</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2014/07/user-interface-display-initial-design/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2014 10:31:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2014/07/user-interface-display-initial-design/</guid>
      <description>Following on from working on the main data switches in my last post this time I&amp;rsquo;ve taken the first steps in designing and constructing the first of two display cards which will sit in the upper enclosure. The first card (display A) has a dual purpose &amp;hellip; it provides a display to show which control signals are in operation between the various parts of the computer but also allows the operator to manually control those signals when the computer is set to a special &amp;lsquo;diagnostic&amp;rsquo; mode.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
