<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ALU Arithmetic Unit on Relay Computer</title>
    <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/arithmetic-unit/</link>
    <description>Recent content in ALU Arithmetic Unit on Relay Computer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2014 17:31:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/arithmetic-unit/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>ALU Construction: Completed Arithmetic Card Full Test</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2014/02/alu-construction-completed-arithmetic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2014 17:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2014/02/alu-construction-completed-arithmetic/</guid>
      <description>The ALU arithmetic card is now complete! The final card looks like this:
As I did for the ALU logic card before I&amp;rsquo;ve put the following YouTube video together which gives a walkthrough of the arithmetic card in operation &amp;hellip; and as before this one also has a narrative track delivered by my own fair gob.
So, that&amp;rsquo;s two out of the three ALU cards done with just the control card left to do.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ALU Construction: Arithmetic Card Wire Wrap 2</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2014/02/alu-construction-arithmetic-card-wire_19/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2014 22:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2014/02/alu-construction-arithmetic-card-wire_19/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve managed to squeeze in a couple more wire wrapping sessions this week so in this post there&amp;rsquo;s a few photos of progress so far.
Inputs B and C are fully wired in now as is the data bus output. As all the wiring is now complete on the arithmetic 1-bit units I&amp;rsquo;ve popped the relays in.
The next wire links to add are the control lines which select either the Add or Increment operation and then once that&amp;rsquo;s done the card should be ready for powering up and testing/debugging.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ALU Construction: Arithmetic Card Wire Wrap 1</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2014/02/alu-construction-arithmetic-card-wire/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2014 10:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2014/02/alu-construction-arithmetic-card-wire/</guid>
      <description>Fear not (just in case you were for some reason) all this talk of Sketchup and enclosures and so on hasn&amp;rsquo;t totally diverted me from the main task of constructing the ALU. The wire wrap is coming along nicely on the arithmetic card although it has taken slightly more concentration than before to get all the wraps in the right places.
Here&amp;rsquo;s a couple of pictures showing the card in its current state of progress:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ALU Construction: Arithmetic Card Power Rails</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2014/01/alu-construction-arithmetic-card-power/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2014 23:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2014/01/alu-construction-arithmetic-card-power/</guid>
      <description>Another round of soldering done &amp;hellip; this time putting down the power rails on the arithmetic card along with some soldered wire links. This is the last of the soldering for this card - it&amp;rsquo;s all wire wrapping form hereon in.
The rear of the card now looks like this:
The power rails are very similar to the ones of the logic card completed earlier and they were just as fiddly to complete too &amp;hellip; although, that said, I do seem to be developing a bit of a &amp;lsquo;sixth sense&amp;rsquo; for how long a wire should be cut without measuring it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ALU Construction: 1-bit Arithmetic Full Construction</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2014/01/alu-construction-1-bit-arithmetic-full/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2014 18:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2014/01/alu-construction-1-bit-arithmetic-full/</guid>
      <description>So, as mentioned in my last post this time I&amp;rsquo;ve put in the wire links and wraps needed to test the first bit of the arithmetic card. With these in place I can make sure everything works as it should before repeating it all eight times over to make the full 8-bit adder.
As a quick reminder here&amp;rsquo;s the diagram for the 1-bit full adder:
Reproducing this on the arithmetic card gives the following (on the front of the card):</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ALU Construction: Arithmetic Card Relay Sockets</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2014/01/alu-construction-arithmetic-card-relay/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2014 23:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2014/01/alu-construction-arithmetic-card-relay/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s always a fiddly job getting the relay sockets soldered in and the ALU arithmetic card proved no exception. With this in mind I&amp;rsquo;ve been spreading the work out over several mini sessions in accordance with my new post-Xmas lack of patience. Therefore it&amp;rsquo;s taken me a bit longer than it would otherwise to complete this stage of construction although to be fair I also got distracted with a Nixie clock kit my partner bought me for Christmas &amp;hellip; and I ran out of solder (this time though I&amp;rsquo;ve finally stumped up the cash to buy a 500g reel which should keep me going for a good while).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ALU Construction: Arithmetic Card Header Pins</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2014/01/alu-construction-arithmetic-card-header/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2014 22:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2014/01/alu-construction-arithmetic-card-header/</guid>
      <description>Following on from the successful construction of the ALU logic card in my last post it&amp;rsquo;s time to start off the new year with the next ALU card (number 2 of 3 ALU cards in total) &amp;hellip; the arithmetic card. As for the logic card I&amp;rsquo;ll begin by soldering down all the header pins that will be wire wrapped to later on (the LEDs and connectors were already added to this card earlier).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ALU Construction: LED Tests</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2013/12/alu-construction-led-tests/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2013 20:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2013/12/alu-construction-led-tests/</guid>
      <description>Following on from my last post I can now test the LEDs that have been soldered and hooked up to the header pins on each of the three ALU cards (Logic, Arithmetic and Control). As promised, here are the videos of said testing:
You might notice I&amp;rsquo;m prodding around slightly more carefully on the arithmetic and control cards &amp;hellip; due to a lack of foresight I&amp;rsquo;ve ended up with every second header pin being a direct line to 0v &amp;hellip; which is not great when the thing I&amp;rsquo;m holding has 12v at the tip.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ALU Construction: LED Header Pins</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2013/12/alu-construction-led-header-pins/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2013 21:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2013/12/alu-construction-led-header-pins/</guid>
      <description>So far, in the construction of the three ALU cards (Logic, Arithmetic and Control) I&amp;rsquo;ve soldered down the connectors and LEDs. It&amp;rsquo;s now time to solder in some header pins and join them to the existing connectors and LEDs ready for wire-wrapping later.
You can get proper wire-wrap posts but they&amp;rsquo;re really expensive for what they are (mainly, I guess, because it&amp;rsquo;s quite an old-fashioned construction method). I&amp;rsquo;ve found, though, that header pins do the job just as well but being as they&amp;rsquo;re not as tall you can only get a maximum of two wraps on each pin.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ALU Construction: Connectors and LEDs</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2013/12/alu-construction-connectors-and-leds/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2013 18:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2013/12/alu-construction-connectors-and-leds/</guid>
      <description>As promised in my last post it&amp;rsquo;s finally time to get the soldering iron out and make a start on constructing the three cards that make up the ALU. I&amp;rsquo;m going start by laying down the connectors and LEDs on each card to make sure I&amp;rsquo;m happy with the look and feel of things and then I can move on to everything else needed later.
As mentioned in earlier posts I&amp;rsquo;m basing my construction around 55 x 40 hole pad boards which fit my designs quite nicely at the right sort of size I&amp;rsquo;m looking to construct at.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ALU Design: 8-bit Arithmetic Unit</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2013/11/design-8-bit-arithmetic-unit/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2013 10:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2013/11/design-8-bit-arithmetic-unit/</guid>
      <description>In the last post I introduced the design for the 1-bit Arithmetic Unit. This post covers connecting eight of these units together to make an 8-bit Arithmetic Unit along with result gating and increment functionality.
So, diving straight in, here is what eight of the 1-bit Arithmetic Units look like all together on the usual 55 x 40 hole pad board (excluding wire lines):
8 x 1-bit Arithmetic Unit Relays (larger) As before (with the Logic Unit card) things are a bit on the tight side but everything fits within the 40 hole horizontal confines of the pad board (as if by magic).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ALU Design: 1-bit Arithmetic Unit</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2013/11/design-1-bit-arithmetic-unit/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2013 22:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2013/11/design-1-bit-arithmetic-unit/</guid>
      <description>This post covers the design of a 1-bit Arithmetic Unit that can add two input bits together (B and C) with carry in and out. Here&amp;rsquo;s a schematic of the 1-bit Arithmetic Unit (based directly on the one used in the Harry Porter Relay Computer):
The diagram shows two 4PDT relays (just as before for the 1-bit Logic Unit) but this time the second relay has been rotated 180 degrees to make the diagram simpler to draw.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
