<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pages on Relay Computer</title>
    <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/pages/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pages on Relay Computer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language><atom:link href="https://relaycomputer.co.uk/pages/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>ALU Summary</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/pages/alu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/pages/alu/</guid>
      <description>The Arithmetic Logic Unit (ALU) is split into three units (and also three physical cards): the logic unit, the arithmetic unit and the control unit. The logic and arithmetic cards handle 8-bit logic and arithmetic functions respectively. The control unit handles function decoding, zero detection and holds the condition registers.
Details of the design, construction and testing of each unit can be found in the following:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assembly</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/pages/assembly/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/pages/assembly/</guid>
      <description>Although the computer is primarily controlled by a set of 8-bit opcodes these can be tricky to work with when designing more complicated programs. As with many computers we can use a higher-level language which is more readable for a human but then will need converting into 8-bit opcodes for the computer to understand.
I have designed an assembly style language which is made up of a series of mnemonics that each map directly to an equivalent opcode.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Control Summary</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/pages/control/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/pages/control/</guid>
      <description>The computer is controlled by a series of instructions held in memory (a computer program) that are loaded into the instruction register one at a time and executed. The execution of an instruction is performed by running a clock signal through a sequencer which produces a series of pulses. These pulses are then used to operate the control lines of the computer at the right time and in the right order appropriate for the current instruction.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enclosure Summary</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/pages/enclosure/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/pages/enclosure/</guid>
      <description>The enclosure for the computer is based on an aluminium profile frame with laser cut acrylic and plywood panelling. The original design was put together in the excellent SketchUp software before ordering the parts and moving on to the physical construction. The enclosure consists of an upper and lower unit with the lower unit containing all the various cards of the computer and the upper unit primarily acting as a display.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Instructions</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/pages/instructions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/pages/instructions/</guid>
      <description>The computer is controlled by a series of instructions held in memory (a computer program) that are loaded into the instruction register one at a time and executed. Each instruction is formed of an 8-bit &amp;lsquo;op-code&amp;rsquo; and falls in to a class of related instructions (identifiable by the leading part of the op-code).
The list of available instructions is as follows:
ALU Operation ALU 8 1 0 0 0 r f f f r = destination register (0-A, 1-D)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Overview</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/pages/overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/pages/overview/</guid>
      <description>This blog documents my journey in constructing an 8-bit relay computer, from scratch, made from tons of solder, wires, lights, relays, sweat, tears, swearing and money.
The design of the computer is based on the one constructed by Dr. Harry Porter at Portland State University (reproduced on this blog with kind permission) but the construction method is my own and so this blog captures the thoughts, experiences and pitfalls that I encounter along the way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Progress Summary</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/pages/progress/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/pages/progress/</guid>
      <description> Bay W Bay X Bay Y Bay Z Others Depreciated Cards &amp;nbsp;Complete Backplane W v2 More Info | | &amp;nbsp;Complete Backplane W Daughterboard More Info &amp;nbsp;Complete Decoder v2 More Info | | | &amp;nbsp;Part-Complete Controller v2 upper&amp;nbsp; More Info | | | &amp;nbsp;Complete Controller v2 lower&amp;nbsp; More Info | | | &amp;nbsp;Complete Sequencer v2 upper&amp;nbsp; More Info | | | &amp;nbsp;Complete Sequencer v2 lower&amp;nbsp; More Info | | | &amp;nbsp;Complete Backplane X More Info &amp;nbsp;Complete Clock More Info | | | &amp;nbsp;Complete Incrementer More Info | &amp;nbsp;Complete Instruction Register More Info | &amp;nbsp;Complete Program Counter More Info | &amp;nbsp;Designed Backplane Y v2 More Info | | &amp;nbsp;Designed Backplane Y Daughterboard More Info &amp;nbsp;Complete Memory More Info | &amp;nbsp;Complete Register J More Info | | | &amp;nbsp;Complete Register M More Info | | | &amp;nbsp;Complete Register XY More Info | | | &amp;nbsp;Designed Backplane Z v2 More Info | | &amp;nbsp;Designed Backplane Z Daughterboard More Info &amp;nbsp;Complete ALU Arithmetic Unit More Info | &amp;nbsp;Complete ALU Control Unit More Info | &amp;nbsp;Complete ALU Logic Unit More Info | &amp;nbsp;Complete Register A/D More Info | &amp;nbsp;Complete Register B/C More Info | &amp;nbsp;Complete Auxiliary Control More Info | &amp;nbsp;Part-Complete Display A More Info | &amp;nbsp;Part-Complete Display B More Info | &amp;nbsp;Part-Complete Enclosure More Info &amp;nbsp;Complete Test Board More Info &amp;nbsp;Abandoned Backplane W v1 More Info &amp;nbsp;Abandoned Backplane Y v1 More Info | &amp;nbsp;Abandoned Backplane Z v1 More Info &amp;nbsp;Abandoned Controller v1 More Info | &amp;nbsp;Abandoned Decoder v1 More Info | &amp;nbsp;Abandoned Sequencer v1 More Info | </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Registers Summary</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/pages/registers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/pages/registers/</guid>
      <description>The computer has eight general purpose 8-bit registers named A, B, C, D, M1, M2, X and Y. Although each can be used generally some of the registers have additional specific uses. Register B and C feed the ALU inputs, M1 and M2 form a 16-bit memory pointer (M) and X and Y form a 16-bit memory pointer (XY) typically used to store a return address when performing jumps.
In addition to the general purpose registers there are five special registers named J1, J2, the instruction register, the program counter and the ALU condition code register.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UI Summary</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/pages/ui/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/pages/ui/</guid>
      <description>The computer&amp;rsquo;s user interface is comprised of two display cards (A and B) and then a row of data and control switches. Display A shows the state of the various control signals and allows the user to manually set those signals when the computer is placed in the &amp;lsquo;diagnostic mode&amp;rsquo;. Display B likewise shows other control signals but these are read only. Additionally Display B also shows the state of the data and address busses and shows the current consumption of the computer.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
