<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Register J on Relay Computer</title>
    <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/register-j/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Register J on Relay Computer</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2019 01:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/register-j/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>16-bit Register PCB Design</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2019/08/16bit-register-pcb-design/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2019 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2019/08/16bit-register-pcb-design/</guid>
      <description>It’s time for the oddly therapeutic part of designing a PCB … laying out the board. In my last post I covered the schematic design and so we now have all the components required for a 16-bit register captured in my design program of choice (EasyEDA) along with how each component is connected to everything else. The next step is to generate a PCB layout from that schematic … and I say ‘generate’ which perhaps makes it sound like it’s a ‘click of a button’ type thing … well, clicking the ‘create PCB’ button results in this:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16-bit Register Design</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2019/07/16bit-register-design/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2019 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2019/07/16bit-register-design/</guid>
      <description>In my last couple of posts I’ve been building up to a change of approach in how I’m making the cards in my computer. This is mainly because I can’t face the monotony of hand building the upcoming register cards (which I’ll need three of so it’s triple the procrastination holding me back). The obvious solution to all of this is to create a Printed Circuit Board (PCB) which will cut out most of the trickier soldering and pretty much all the repetitive wirewrap … and that looked like the way to go until I had a go at hand crafting a simplified PCB for the Y backplane and I realised it’s not as easy as it might otherwise appear.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
