<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Power Distribution on Relay Computer</title>
    <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/power-dist/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Power Distribution on Relay Computer</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Oct 2017 11:01:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://relaycomputer.co.uk/cards/power-dist/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Miscellany Special: Power Distribution</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2017/10/miscellany-special-power-distribution/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Oct 2017 11:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2017/10/miscellany-special-power-distribution/</guid>
      <description>Having somehow forgotten to take time off work I’m now playing ‘annual leave catch up’ which means lots of four day weeks but also, and more importantly for this blog, I’m getting time to crack on with construction of my relay computer. The current milestone I’m working towards is finishing off the Program Counter, Incrementer and Memory cards (which are all well under way now) so that I can load a simple program in to the computer and set it running without any further intervention.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>W Backplane Construction &amp; Power Distribution</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2016/04/w-backplane-construction-power/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2016 21:07:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2016/04/w-backplane-construction-power/</guid>
      <description>Before I can test the new decoder, sequencer and controller cards all working together with the rest of the computer I need to construct the ‘W’ backplane which the new cards sit on. Generally this backplane is similar in design to the ‘Z’ backplane that the ALU cards and A/D and B/C register cards sit on. However, whereas each card on the Z backplane has the exact same connectors the W backplane is slightly more complex as the sequencer and control units are spread over two cards each requiring a different set of connectors. The upshot is that the backplane has three ‘W1’ card slots and two ‘W2’ card slots. A diagram explains it better:</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
