<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>musings on Relay Computer</title>
    <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/tags/musings/</link>
    <description>Recent content in musings on Relay Computer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2019 11:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://relaycomputer.co.uk/tags/musings/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A change of approach</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2019/01/change-of-approach/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2019 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2019/01/change-of-approach/</guid>
      <description>In my last post I touched on how the repetitive nature of making register cards has been putting me off progressing my relay computer. If you&amp;rsquo;ve followed my blog (over the years) you&amp;rsquo;ll have witnessed the construction of the general purpose registers A, B, C and D along with the specialised registers in the incrementer and program counter. Each register card follows the same construction pattern: solder down LEDs, solder down relay sockets, solder down wire wrap posts, solder ground and power lines, wire wrap, wire wrap, wire wrap, wire wrap, etc, etc, insert relays in sockets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Procrastination is the thief of time</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2019/01/procrastination-is/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jan 2019 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2019/01/procrastination-is/</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip; or so the proverb goes &amp;hellip; and it&amp;rsquo;s fair to say I&amp;rsquo;ve been procrastinating quite a bit recently.
I typically take a summer break from working on the relay computer so that I can service all the other hobbies I have on the go but also to enjoy the brief warm weather we get here in the UK. Usually come autumn time I&amp;rsquo;m back building, blogging and making videos but this year &amp;lsquo;summer&amp;rsquo; has hung on &amp;hellip; through to the end of the year no less &amp;hellip; and it&amp;rsquo;s because I&amp;rsquo;m intentionally/unintentionally putting off getting started.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The problem with memory</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2017/08/the-problem-with-memory/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Aug 2017 22:58:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2017/08/the-problem-with-memory/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s time, at last, to start looking at the design for the computer&amp;rsquo;s memory and this is a bit of a game changer as it&amp;rsquo;s the final part of the jigsaw that lets the computer run a program. However, it&amp;rsquo;s also the part of the computer that leaves me in a bit of a quandary.
The problem with memory is that typically you need quite a lot of it and that&amp;rsquo;s something that doesn&amp;rsquo;t come easy with relays.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enclosure Disclosure</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2014/03/enclosure-disclosure/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Mar 2014 10:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2014/03/enclosure-disclosure/</guid>
      <description>Sorry, I will try to rain in the terrible punning post titles.
This time I wanted to share the thoughts and ideas I&amp;rsquo;ve been having around building a case to hold my computer when it&amp;rsquo;s eventually complete. I wanted to use a material that would be easy to handle and work with but also one that would produce a nice looking result. I was initially drawn to using wood or possibly even laser cut plywood but in the end I settled on aluminium profile as its sturdy, easy to assemble and, I think, looks really great.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sketchy Diversion</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2014/02/sketchy-diversion/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2014 19:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2014/02/sketchy-diversion/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m taking a break &amp;hellip; just a short one.
In between all the bouts of wire wrapping for the ALU arithmetic card I&amp;rsquo;m starting to think about enclosure options for the computer when it&amp;rsquo;s finally (finally!) finished. I&amp;rsquo;ve been trawling the internet for inspiration and I&amp;rsquo;m starting to get a feel for the sort of materials and finish I want and I&amp;rsquo;ve even been getting some prototype laser etching done (more on this in a later post).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Relay Rumination</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2013/11/relay-rumination/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2013 23:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2013/11/relay-rumination/</guid>
      <description>If there&amp;rsquo;s one thing a relay computer needs a lot of it&amp;rsquo;s &amp;hellip; erm &amp;hellip; relays (of course) &amp;hellip; which happens to be a bit unfortunate as relays, compared to the other parts of the computer, are rather expensive. The Dr Harry Porter Relay Computer (which my computer is based on) uses 415 x 4PDT (4 pole double toggle) relays in total. A comparable part is the Omron MY4-DC12(S) relay and a quick check online with Mouser (other suppliers are available ;) prices them around £3.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The three Rs</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2013/11/the-three-rs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2013 09:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2013/11/the-three-rs/</guid>
      <description>It strikes me that when embarking on a project like this there&amp;rsquo;s three things that are of uttermost importance, the three Rs if you will:
Research, research and research.
There&amp;rsquo;s a lot to be said for experimentation and working things out but the human race wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have got very far it didn&amp;rsquo;t share knowledge and learn from each others mistakes. So naturally, if I want to build my own computer from scratch I should start out by doing lots of reading about how old computers were built.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why?</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2013/11/why/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2013 10:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2013/11/why/</guid>
      <description>Whenever I tell people I&amp;rsquo;m building a relay computer the overwhelming response is &amp;hellip; why on Earth would you want to do that?! Or alternatively, as a work colleague delicately put it to me yesterday, if you go to the front of your house there&amp;rsquo;s a big block of wood that opens — it&amp;rsquo;s called a door — if you go through it you&amp;rsquo;ll discover pubs and things. They&amp;rsquo;ve all got a point though, this project will be very time consuming and I&amp;rsquo;ve not particularly got a use in mind for the resulting jumble of wires.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It begins</title>
      <link>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2013/10/it-begins/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2013 22:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://relaycomputer.co.uk/posts/2013/10/it-begins/</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip; although being as I&amp;rsquo;m already a couple of months in on my little project then perhaps that should be &amp;lsquo;it began&amp;rsquo;.
If I do see this project all the way through to the end, and I&amp;rsquo;ve plenty of half finished projects littering the place by the way, then I&amp;rsquo;ll have created an 8 bit computer from scratch. No, not a PC assembled from off the shelf parts — a CPU, motherboard, memory, power supply, case, etc — but made out of a ton of solder, wires, lights, relays, sweat, tears, swearing and money.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
